<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cain and Abel parallel'd with King Charles and his murderers in a sermon preached in S. Thomas Church in Salisbury, Jan. 30, 1663, being the anniversary day of the martyrdom of King Charles I of blessed memory / by Henry Glover ...</title>
            <author>Glover, Henry, b. 1624 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9147</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13110049</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13110049</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97614</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42868)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97614)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 418:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cain and Abel parallel'd with King Charles and his murderers in a sermon preached in S. Thomas Church in Salisbury, Jan. 30, 1663, being the anniversary day of the martyrdom of King Charles I of blessed memory / by Henry Glover ...</title>
                  <author>Glover, Henry, b. 1624 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. Cotes for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97614:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97614:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CAIN and ABEL PARALLEL'D With King CHARLES and his Murderers. IN A SERMON Preached in S. <hi>Thomas</hi> Church in <hi>Salisbury, Jan.</hi> 30. 1663. Being the Anniverſary Day of the Martyrdom of King CHARLES I. of Bleſſed Memory.</p>
            <p>By HENRY GLOVER Rector of <hi>Shroton</hi> in the County of <hi>Dorſet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 King. 9. 31.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Had</hi> Zimri <hi>peace who ſlew his Maſter?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Cotes</hi> for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> in <hi>Ivy-lane,</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:97614:2"/>
            <p>PErlegi hanc Concionem, cui Titulus (Cain <hi>and</hi> Abel <hi>parallel'd with King</hi> Charles <hi>and his Murderers,</hi>) in quâ nihil occurrit Doctrinae, Diſciplinaeve Eccleſiae An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicanae, aut bonis moribus contrarium.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joh. Hall <hi>R. P. D. Epiſc.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>Lond.
<hi>à Sac. Domeſt.</hi> 
                  <date>Mar. 29. 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97614:2"/>
            <head>To my Reverend Brother <hi>THOMAS HIDE</hi> D. D. and Chanter of the Cathedral Church in <hi>SALISBURY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ſolicitous to give the World any other <hi>account</hi> of the publiſhing of this <hi>Sermon,</hi> but only this, That it was Preached at your <hi>Motion,</hi> and is now prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at your <hi>Requeſt;</hi> which was (it ſeems) animated by others of my then <hi>Auditors,</hi> who deſired to <hi>ſee</hi> what they had <hi>heard,</hi> and to have that in their <hi>hands,</hi> which otherwiſe was too apt to ſlip through their <hi>ears.</hi> What <hi>Cenſures</hi> I may undergo for this my <hi>compliance</hi> with your and their deſires, I am not able to divine; if it be from <hi>Wiſe men,</hi> remember you are either to bear the <hi>Blame,</hi> or to make my <hi>Apology;</hi> if from others, I hope I ſhall be able to bear the weight of their <hi>diſpleaſure</hi> my ſelf, and to requite their <hi>cenſures</hi> with <hi>neglect.</hi> For the <hi>Sermon,</hi> I have only this to ſay of it, That it was intended to upbraid none but the <hi>guilty,</hi> and among them none but the <hi>impenitent;</hi> and even to them the onely harm intended was
<pb facs="tcp:97614:3"/>
but this, to ſet before them, as in a Glaſs, the <hi>hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs</hi> of their ſin, that it might be a means (with Gods bleſſing) to accelerate their <hi>converſion,</hi> and rouze them up from that <hi>Lethargy</hi> of a <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>dedolent diſpoſition</hi> of heart, in which the moſt of them lie yet ſleeping; <hi>If God per adventure will give</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 19.</note> 
               <hi>them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth, that they may recover themſelves out of the ſnare of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who are taken captive by him at his will,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 25, 26. Of the <hi>Principals,</hi> I muſt confeſs, I think there is but little hope; but for the <hi>Acceſſaries,</hi> I hope they have not all ſinned the <hi>ſin unto death;</hi> and therefore for them I ſhall put up S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> prayer (upon that paſſage of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Let them be aſhamed and confounded,</hi> &amp;c. Pſ. 70. 2.) <hi>Sic confun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantur</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Enarr. in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.</note> 
               <hi>ut convertantur, quia converti non poſſunt, niſi confuſi fuerint;</hi> let them ſo be <hi>aſhamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,</hi> that they may be <hi>amended and converted;</hi> becauſe they cannot be <hi>converted,</hi> unleſs they be ſo <hi>confounded.</hi> If this Sermon ſhould prove inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to do any ſuch good upon any one of their ſouls, I ſhould look upon it as a great <hi>bleſsing</hi> both to them and me. But leaving the ſucceſs of that to God, I ſhall content my ſelf at preſent with this <hi>demonſtration</hi> of my readineſs to ſerve you, and ſo remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your loving Brother,
<hi>Henry Glover.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97614:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CAIN and ABEL PARALLEL'D With King CHARLES and his Murderers.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>GEN. 4. 10, 11.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And he ſaid, What haſt thou done? The voice of thy Brothers bloud crieth unto me from the ground.</p>
                  <p>And now art thou curſed from the Earth, which hath opened her mouth to receive thy Brothers bloud from thy hand.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I had the Liberty of chooſing a <hi>Text</hi> this day, not onely out of the <hi>Sacred Bible,</hi> but out of any other <hi>Hiſtory</hi> in the world, I ſuppoſe it would be impoſſible to find a <hi>Parallel</hi> for that <hi>Tragedy</hi> which <hi>England</hi> this day ſaw acted; there never having been ſuch a <hi>piece of Villany</hi> acted in the World before. It is ſtoried of <hi>Conradinus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Conrade</hi> the fourth, the laſt of the Noble Family of the <hi>Barbaroſſae,</hi> that being taken Priſoner in Battel by <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> he was by the Inſtigation of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth, publiquely <hi>beheaded</hi> at <hi>Naples.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:97614:4"/>
Here was a <hi>King beheaded,</hi> but then he had the honour to be <hi>beheaded</hi> by a <hi>King,</hi> not by a Tumultuous Rabble of his own <hi>Rebellious Subjects;</hi> and which is more, the <hi>Headſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> who did the Execution, was preſently <hi>beheaded</hi> by another, <hi>Ne extaret qui diceret tam generoſum ſanguinem à ſe effuſum:</hi> that there might not be one able to <hi>boaſt</hi> that he ſhed that <hi>Noble blood.</hi> Here was ſome reſpect had to <hi>Majeſty,</hi> but not ſo with our <hi>Regicides.</hi> The <hi>ſacred blood</hi> which they ſhed was <hi>vilely caſt away,</hi> as if the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> whoſe blood it was, <hi>had not been anointed with Oyl,</hi> 2 Sam. 1. 21. It being then impoſſible to find a Text that ſhould repreſent this days Villany <hi>to the Life,</hi> we muſt be content with one that will do it, although in <hi>fainter colours.</hi> And truly I think this of <hi>Cain</hi> (the <hi>oldeſt Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer</hi> in the World, except onely his <hi>Father the Devil,</hi> who was a-<hi>Murderer from the Beginning</hi>) will come clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt home to our <hi>Engliſh Cainites,</hi> or rather <hi>Canibals,</hi> (who were the <hi>greateſt Murderers</hi> in the World, the <hi>Devil himſelf</hi> not excepted.) <hi>Wo unto them, for they have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the way of</hi> Cain, <hi>Jude</hi> 11. And then the ſufferings of <hi>Abel the firſt Martyr,</hi> will beſt expreſs the ſufferings of <hi>King Charles the greateſt Martyr</hi> in the World. Thus the day is <hi>a day of blood,</hi> and the Text is <hi>a Text of blood; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> blood both, <hi>crying</hi> blood, and both accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with a <hi>Curſe</hi> upon the Shedders: The Lord ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Cain, What haſt thou done? the voice of thy Brothers blood crieth unto me from the ground. And now thou art curſed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will obſerve in the Text but theſe two general Parts, <hi>a Cry</hi> and <hi>a Curſe;</hi> a <hi>great Cry,</hi> and a <hi>great Curſe;</hi> the cry of <hi>Blood,</hi> and the curſe of the <hi>Blood ſhedder.</hi> Both theſe we ſhall ſee exactly fulfilled, as well in <hi>King Charles</hi> and his Murderers, as in <hi>Abel</hi> and his. Where they run
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97614:4"/>
parallel, I ſhall endeavour to compare them; and where they out-go <hi>Cain</hi> in Impudence and Villany, I ſhall as I paſs along, take notice of it. And ſo I begin with the firſt part of my Text, a <hi>Cry,</hi> a <hi>great Cry, The voice of thy Brothers blood crieth unto me from the ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be four ſorts of ſins eſpecially, that are ſaid in Scripture to have a <hi>Voice;</hi> and though <hi>men</hi> do not hear the <hi>Voice</hi> of theſe ſins, yet <hi>God</hi> doth. They are,</p>
            <p>1. <hi>The cry of bloud</hi> here in this Text. <hi>Murther</hi> hath a Voice, and a ſhrill Voice: though it be but the <hi>blood</hi> of the meaneſt <hi>innocent Subject,</hi> it never leaves clamour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till <hi>expiation</hi> is made by the <hi>blood</hi> of the <hi>Murtherer.</hi> And God hath a <hi>Court of Inquiſition</hi> for ſuch bloody ſins, Pſal. 9. 12. <hi>When he maketh Inquiſition for blood he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth them, and forgetteth not the</hi> Cry <hi>of the humble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The <hi>cry</hi> of that filthy, unnatural ſin of <hi>Sodomy, Men with men working that which is unſeemly,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 27. And this is a very crying ſin; <hi>Gen. 18. 20. The cry of Sodome and Gomorrah is great, and their ſin is very grievous.</hi> Thoſe luſtful <hi>Benjamites</hi> which we read of <hi>Judg.</hi> 19. 22. were unnatural <hi>Sodomites: Bring forth the Man</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that came unto thee, that we may know him.</hi> And there went up a cry from <hi>Gibeah</hi> for that nights work, that was never appeaſed, till almoſt the whole Tribe was deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>The Cry of the oppreſſed,</hi> groaning by reaſon of their Affliction, under the Bondage of their <hi>Tyrannical Task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters;</hi> and God hears the cry of ſuch afflicated, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſouls, <hi>Exod. 2. 23. The children of Iſrael ſighed by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their bondage, and they cried, and their cry came up unto God.</hi> Thus when men by <hi>oppreſsion</hi> and <hi>rapine</hi> do
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97614:5"/>
ſet their <hi>Neſts</hi> on high, there is a <hi>cry</hi> of the very <hi>Stones and Timber</hi> againſt the unjuſt Builder; <hi>The ſtone cries out of the wall, and the beam out of the timber doth anſwer it, Hab.</hi> 2. 11.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>The Cry</hi> of the poor <hi>Labourers hire</hi> detained from him by <hi>fraud</hi> or <hi>violence,</hi> and that <hi>cry entereth into the ears of the Lord of Sabaoth, Jam.</hi> 5. 4. When the poor man is defrauded of his wages on <hi>Earth,</hi> he ſues for it in <hi>Heaven, in forma pauperis;</hi> and God will ſurely hear his cry, and puniſh thee for not paying of him, <hi>Prov. 22. 22, 23. Rob not the poor, becauſe he is poor, neither oppreſs the afflicted in the Gate: For the Lord will plead their cauſe, and ſpoil the ſoul of thoſe that ſpoiled them.</hi> This denotes the <hi>grievouſneſs</hi> of theſe four ſins that they have every one of them a <hi>voice,</hi> crying in the ears of the Lord for <hi>vengeance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This in the Text, is the firſt of theſe, <hi>The voice of blood. Innocent blood</hi> you may be ſure, for <hi>Guilty blood</hi> hath no voice. The blood of a <hi>Malefactor</hi> let out by the <hi>hand of Juſtice</hi> for the preſervation of the <hi>Body Politique,</hi> makes no more noiſe in the ears of God, then the bloud that is let out of a <hi>vein</hi> by the <hi>hand of a skilful Phyſician,</hi> for the preſervation of the <hi>Body Natural.</hi> So when a <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers blood</hi> is ſhed by the Magiſtrate, it hath no voice, its <hi>dumb blood;</hi> becauſe God hath commanded it to be ſhed, <hi>Gen. 9. 6. Whoſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed.</hi> This then is <hi>Innocent blood</hi> (we are ſure) becauſe it hath a <hi>voice.</hi> And was not the blood that was ſhed this day ſuch? Yes certainly; If <hi>Abels blood</hi> had a voice, this could not be ſtill. The ſame ground of quarrel that <hi>Cain</hi> had againſt his innocent brother, theſe <hi>Regicides</hi> had againſt their King: what that was S. <hi>John</hi> will tell you, 1 <hi>Joh. 3. 12. Cain was of that wicked
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97614:5"/>
one, and ſlew his brother; and wherefore ſlew he him? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his own works were evil, and his Brothers righteous.</hi> This was it, and this made them both not onely <hi>innocent</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Civ. Dei lib. 15 c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Sufferers,</hi> but <hi>eminent Martyrs. Facibus invidiae inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur in Fratrem,</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Aug.</hi> of <hi>Cain) &amp; quem debuerat imitari, cupiebat auferre. Cain</hi> envied his brother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was more righteous then himſelf, and ſo thirſted for his bloud, whoſe vertues he ought to have imitated. Had theſe <hi>Murtherers</hi> but lookt with a Chriſtian eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the vertues of the <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> his eminent <hi>Patience,</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> his conſtant <hi>Courage,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> rather to dye then do any thing unbeſeeming a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and a <hi>King,</hi> they had had a fair Copy to have written after, and had never left their <hi>Names</hi> with ſuch a <hi>curſe</hi> upon them to <hi>Poſterity.</hi> But the Devil of <hi>Envy and Diſcontent</hi> was entered into their hearts (as he did into the heart of <hi>Judas,</hi>) and that together with thoſe other <hi>Fiends</hi> of <hi>Covetouſneſs, Ambition,</hi> and <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> ſet them upon this <hi>Helliſh Project.</hi> Thus <hi>Eſau</hi> being diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented becauſe his brother had the <hi>Bleſsing,</hi> vowed his death. Thus <hi>Cain</hi> being diſcontented becauſe his Brothers <hi>Offering</hi> was more acceptable to God, ſhed his bloud. Thus <hi>Ahabs</hi> diſcontent, becauſe he could not have his <hi>Neighbours Vineyard,</hi> coſt innocent <hi>Naboth</hi> his life; and <hi>when he had killed, he took poſſeſſion.</hi> Thus <hi>Judas</hi> being diſcontented (as it is conceived) becauſe he could not get money for the <hi>Oyntment</hi> that anointed our Saviours feet, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. 5.) went away to the Prieſts, and betrayed his Maſter. And laſtly, thus the <hi>Devil</hi> not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his place in <hi>Heaven,</hi> rebelled againſt his <hi>Maker,</hi> and thereupon procured for himſelf a place in <hi>Hell.</hi> Now, put all theſe together, <hi>Cain, Eſau, Ahab, Judas,</hi> and the <hi>Devil;</hi> make up (if you can) one <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97614:6"/>
of their ſeveral ſins, <hi>Envy, Malice, Diſcontent, Pride, Ambition,</hi> and <hi>Sacriledge; beat them</hi> all together till they are become <hi>one great ſin,</hi> and you have the very <hi>Picture</hi> of theſe wretched <hi>Regicides,</hi> who acted over <hi>all their ſins</hi> in this <hi>one Murder.</hi> No wonder then to hear of a <hi>Voice,</hi> when <hi>Innocence</hi> is aſſaulted with ſuch a <hi>legion of Fiends</hi> together; what voice it is, you have in the next words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>The Voice of Bloud.</hi> Of Bloud! that's not all. It is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Original, <hi>The voice of blouds.</hi> What is the meaning of that?</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Junius</hi> is of opinion, that it was put in the <hi>Plural Number,</hi> becauſe it was ſhed abroad upon the earth, and ſo ran here and there in <hi>ſtreams,</hi> as if it had been ſeeking out of <hi>new veins</hi> to diſperſe it ſelf in: And ſo though it were but <hi>Bloud</hi> in the body, yet now it was ſhed it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Blouds. Vox ſanguinum,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſanguinis caede fuſi, &amp; huc illuc diſſilientis ex ictu.</hi> And then this expreſſion will ſerve to aggravate the ſin of Murder, and to ſhew the <hi>cruelty</hi> of ſhedding Innocent Bloud. <hi>The Bloud-thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty man</hi> is uſually in Scripture called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a man of blouds,</hi> ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 6. And if it be ſo in the murder of a <hi>private perſon,</hi> if that be a ſin of ſuch a <hi>deep die,</hi> that nothing but <hi>blouds</hi> will ſerve to expreſs the <hi>guilt</hi> of it; what ſhall we ſay of <hi>Rebellious Subjects</hi> ſhedding the bloud of their <hi>lawful Soveraign,</hi> and letting it out <hi>like water</hi> upon the Earth? Surely this is <hi>Blouds</hi> indeed, and more then ſo, if we had more then a <hi>Plural</hi> to expreſs it by. As when you break a <hi>Looking-Glaſs</hi> in pietes, every little bit of it will ſhew you your <hi>face,</hi> and ſo there is not <hi>one face but many,</hi> when the Glaſs is broken: ſo when that <hi>Royal bloud</hi> was ſhed, every drop of it had a <hi>ſeveral voice,</hi> and ſo it was not a <hi>Voice,</hi> but <hi>Voices;</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97614:6"/>
not onely a <hi>Voice of bloud,</hi> but a <hi>Voice of blouds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The <hi>Chaldee Paraphraſe</hi> reads it, <hi>Vox ſanguinis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum,</hi> the voice of the bloud of ſeeds; or <hi>vox ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis familiarum,</hi> the voice of the bloud of Families; or <hi>vox ſanguinis generationum,</hi> (as it is variouſly rendered) the voice of the bloud of Generations. Becauſe it was not <hi>Abels bloud</hi> onely that was ſhed, but the bloud of all his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> of all the <hi>Families,</hi> and <hi>Generations</hi> that ſhould have come out of <hi>his Loins,</hi> if he had not been murdered. The bloud of <hi>Abel</hi> ſhould have run in the veins of many others that were to deſcend from him; ſo that it was the <hi>bloud of families,</hi> the <hi>bloud of Generations,</hi> the <hi>bloud of ſeeds,</hi> which now by being ſhed loſt its <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifical vertue.</hi> God (it ſeems) takes notice of this; and in this reſpect <hi>Cain</hi> was a Murderer, not onely of one, but of many. You may ſee this more clearly in 2 <hi>King. 9. 26. Surely I have ſeen yeſterday the bloud of Naboth, and the bloud of his ſons, ſaith the Lord, and I will requite thee in this plat, ſaith the Lord.</hi> We read of none but <hi>Naboth</hi> that was put to death, no mention of <hi>his ſons</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing murdered with him, in all the hiſtory of his Trial, and condemnation, and execution, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 13, 14. How then was it the <hi>bloud of Naboth, and the bloud of his ſons?</hi> I ſuppoſe they are in the right, who do underſtand it, <hi>De filiis nondum ab eo natis, ſed qui geniti fuiſſent, ſi diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vide Munſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in 2 Reg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9 26.</note> 
               <hi>vixiſset;</hi> Not of thoſe ſons which he had, but of thoſe which he might have had, if he had lived longer. And ſo though his ſons were not murthered <hi>with him,</hi> yet they were murthered <hi>in him.</hi> And God calls <hi>Ahabs family</hi> to account, not only for <hi>Naboths</hi> bloud, but for the <hi>bloud of his ſons</hi> too, which he might have had, had he not been murthered. To bring home this to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe. The <hi>Murderers</hi> of his late Majeſty ſhed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97614:7"/>
more bloud then they were aware of; bleſſed be God, not the <hi>bloud of all his ſeed,</hi> ſo far the Divine Providence would not permit them to go. He hath been pleaſed to preſerve the <hi>ſacred branches</hi> of that <hi>Royal Root,</hi> and to make them flouriſh again, to keep alive that <hi>great Name</hi> in his <hi>Poſterity.</hi> And yet for ought we know, the bloud of ſome of his <hi>Poſterity</hi> was ſhed in his. This we may truly ſay, That one unhappy ſtroke let almoſt all the <hi>bloud</hi> of his <hi>three Kingdoms</hi> out of his <hi>veins;</hi> and 'twas Gods great Mercy that the <hi>whole Land</hi> (which in his fall was left almoſt lifeleſs, and bloudleſs, and ſpiritleſs,) had not <hi>bled it ſelf to death;</hi> which would ſurely have come to paſs, had not God himſelf been pleaſed to ſtop the <hi>iſſue</hi> of that <hi>blond</hi> with his own <hi>hand,</hi> in the <hi>Reſtauration</hi> of our <hi>Gracious Soveraign.</hi> So 'twas <hi>vox ſanguinum,</hi> the voice of blouds. But whoſe bloud was it? that is the next thing.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Vox ſanguinum fratris tui,</hi> the voice of thy <hi>brothers</hi> bloud. That was an horrid act of <hi>inhumanity</hi> indeed. To kill a <hi>ſtranger</hi> is a ſavage act; to deſtroy the <hi>Image of God</hi> in any perſon living (without juſt cauſe) is a grievous ſin: but to kill a <hi>brother,</hi> this dies the ſin of Murder of a deeper <hi>bloud-colour</hi> then ordinary, and leaves a double guilt upon the ſoul. To kill a brother is (as it were) to let the bloud out of a mans <hi>own veins,</hi> when as it is the ſelf ſame bloud that runs in his brothers. A brother in the <hi>Greek Tongue</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe brethren do lye all in one <hi>Womb,</hi> in one <hi>Belly.</hi> And how inhumane is it for thoſe that drew <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>breath</hi> from the ſame <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> to take away that <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>breath</hi> one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? ſo to kill a brother is hainous, but to kill a <hi>pious, innocent</hi> brother, more hainous yet. When a man is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted for his <hi>Piety,</hi> and murthered for his <hi>Innocencie,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97614:7"/>
and ſlain for <hi>Righteouſneſs ſake;</hi> this is not onely to ſtrike at the <hi>Image of God,</hi> and deſtroy that in the man (as every Murderer doth,) but it is to ſtrike at <hi>God himſelf</hi> in the man. When a Chriſtian is thus <hi>wounded,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>bleeds, Act.</hi> 9. 4. The bloud of <hi>Innocents</hi> doth <hi>cry,</hi> but the bloud of <hi>Martyrs</hi> doth <hi>ſhrick</hi> in the ears of the Almighty. And thus was <hi>Cains</hi> ſin aggravated in the perſon whom he ſlew. But alas! <hi>Cain</hi> was a <hi>Saint</hi> to theſe men we are now ſpeaking of. He ſhed the bloud of his <hi>brother,</hi> theſe of their <hi>Father,</hi> even the <hi>Common Father</hi> of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. If we ſhould alter the words a little, and in ſtead of <hi>fratris tui,</hi> ſay <hi>patris tui,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>thy brothers blood,</hi> ſay <hi>thy fathers blood,</hi> we ſhould make the matter a little worſe; but it would ſtill fall ſhort of the ſavage <hi>barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of theſe <hi>Tragical Murtherers.</hi> Had they with <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> killed their own <hi>brother,</hi> or with <hi>Oedipus</hi> their own <hi>father;</hi> had they with <hi>Medea</hi> chopt their <hi>children</hi> in pieces, or kickt the child out of their <hi>wives bellies</hi> with <hi>Nero,</hi> or ript up their <hi>Mothers bowels,</hi> to ſee the place they lay in before they were born; all this had been a ſort of <hi>Piety</hi> to what theſe Monſters did. To be ſhort; <hi>Fratricide</hi> is a hainous ſin, but <hi>Regicide</hi> is far more hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous then that. To kill a man is <hi>homicide,</hi> to kill a father is <hi>parricide,</hi> but to kill a King is <hi>Deicide;</hi> that's but <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter,</hi> but this is a ſort of <hi>God-ſlaughter:</hi> God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf calls them <hi>Gods,</hi> and man is forbid to <hi>curſe them,</hi> much more to <hi>kill them;</hi> he muſt not uſe his <hi>tongue</hi> to their <hi>diſhonour,</hi> much leſs is he permitted to take up a <hi>ſword</hi> for their <hi>deſtruction. Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor curſe the Ruler of thy people, Exod.</hi> 22. 28. You ſee then in reſpect of the <hi>perſon</hi> whom they ſlew, how far theſe men have out-gone <hi>Cain</hi> in villany; and you ſhall ſee the ſame in other reſpects by and by.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97614:8"/>Thus we have <hi>ſeen bloud,</hi> and we have <hi>heard bloud.</hi> The <hi>ſight</hi> of bloud is no pleaſant ſight, and the <hi>voice</hi> of bloud is no pleaſant hearing; eſpecially if you conſider to whom it cries, and for what purpoſe; which is the fourth particular.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Clamat ad me,</hi> ſaith God, it crieth unto me. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here uſed, doth ſignifie <hi>exclamare, vociferari,</hi> to whoop or hollow, to cry out with abundance of <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs</hi> and <hi>violence,</hi> as one that is in any great danger, would do for <hi>help;</hi> and that generally not with any <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate, ſignificative voice,</hi> (that's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) but onely with a <hi>great noiſe,</hi> as if the voice of bloud were that which would even <hi>fill the ears</hi> of God, that he ſhould <hi>hearken</hi> to nothing elſe, till that were avenged. So then it is not a <hi>ſmall, ſtill voice,</hi> but a <hi>loud, fearful, ſhricking voice,</hi> and <hi>clamat ad me,</hi> ſaith God, it crieth unto me, that is, it is a <hi>voice</hi> crying for <hi>Juſtice</hi> to the <hi>Judge</hi> of all the World; a voice crying for <hi>vengeance</hi> to him, <hi>to whom vengeance belongeth.</hi> 'Tis a voice of bloud calling and crying out for bloud, <hi>that they who have ſhed bloud may have bloud to drink; Rev.</hi> 16. 6. Thus doth all <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bloud</hi> cry and ſhriek in the ears of the Almighty. No other innocent bloud that ever was ſhed in the world, hath any other note, but onely the bloud of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> That is indeed <hi>better bloud</hi> then that of <hi>Abel,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſpeaketh better things then that of Abel, Heb.</hi> 12. 24. It cried for <hi>Mercy,</hi> and for Mercy to the very <hi>Murtherers,</hi> whoſe ſouls (ſome of them at leaſt) were waſhed with that very bloud which their hands had ſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 23. with 38. The efficacie and vertue of that <hi>Prayer</hi> of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do,</hi> made that pretious innocent <hi>bloud</hi> a ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign <hi>bath,</hi> to cleanſe their ſouls who had ſhed it. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97614:8"/>
ſo the <hi>bloud of Chriſt</hi> did out-crie even the <hi>bloud of Chriſt;</hi> that is, The voice of Chriſts bloud as <hi>Mediator,</hi> did crie louder for <hi>Mercy,</hi> then the voice of Chriſts bloud as an <hi>innocent Sufferer</hi> did cry for <hi>vengeance.</hi> Thus that bloud cried, and ſtill doth crie for <hi>Mercy;</hi> but all other inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud (having no <hi>merit</hi> in it ſelf to cleanſe ſouls) doth cry for <hi>vengeance,</hi> and will never leave crying till it be revenged. <hi>The ſouls of thoſe that lay under the Altar,</hi> (Rev. 6. 9. <hi>who were ſlain for the word of God, and for the teſtimony which they held, cried with a loud voice, ſaying; How long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our bloud on them that dwell on the Earth?</hi> Not as if thoſe bleſſed ſouls were <hi>Vindictae Cupidi,</hi> or had the leaſt <hi>malice,</hi> or deſire of <hi>revenge</hi> againſt their Murderers. Such an <hi>opinion</hi> will not ſuit with that <hi>happy ſtate of bliſs</hi> in which they are. But as the <hi>bloud of the Sacrifice</hi> (ſaith <hi>Grotius</hi>) which was poured at the <hi>foot of the Altar,</hi> did<note place="margin">Grot. in Apoc. 6. 9.</note> as it were mind God of the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> which was offered up to him upon the <hi>Altar:</hi> So the ſouls of th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe <hi>Martyrs,</hi> which are ſaid to lie <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>under the Altar;</hi> do as it were continually put God in mind of their <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſufferings,</hi> and ſtir up his <hi>juſtice</hi> to take vengeance on their Murderers. So did the bloud of our <hi>Royal Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> crie, and that under the <hi>Altar</hi> too, being ſlain for the <hi>Teſtimony which he held,</hi> and it cried ſo loud, that all his <hi>Kingdoms</hi> heard it from one end to the other, and <hi>ſhook</hi> at the noiſe, and could never have reſt till God heard the crie of it, and avenged it.</p>
            <p>5. Once more, and I have done with the firſt part of my Text. <hi>A voice! a voice of bloud,</hi> of <hi>brothers bloud,</hi> and that <hi>crying bloud;</hi> not whiſpering, but olamouring for vengeance. Now laſtly, From whence doth it cry? Why, <hi>clamat de terra,</hi> it crieth from the ground which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97614:9"/>
had received it from the Murderers hand. As if the <hi>Earth</hi> it ſelf had ſhewed ſome <hi>compaſſion</hi> in drinking of it in, when the <hi>Murderer</hi> ſhewed ſo much <hi>cruelty</hi> in the letting of it out. Or rather, as if the Earth would have hid the bloud, or <hi>Cain</hi> would fain have hid it in the earth, but yet it could not be; for when it was <hi>covered</hi> in the earth, yet ſtill it did <hi>crie;</hi> and when it could not be <hi>ſeen,</hi> yet ſtill it was <hi>heard.</hi> Thus vengeance purſues Murderers, and (as the Poet could tell us) <hi>Raro antecedentem ſceleſtum</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horat.</note> 
               <hi>deſeruit pede poena claudo;</hi> when ſuch bloudy ſins do march in the <hi>Front,</hi> vengeance will not fail to bring up the <hi>Rear.</hi> The very <hi>Barbarians</hi> themſelves had it either from <hi>Experience,</hi> or from <hi>Natural Light,</hi> that <hi>Murderers could not go unpuniſhed:</hi> which made them ſay one to another, when they ſaw the <hi>Viper</hi> hanging on S. <hi>Pauls</hi> hand, <hi>Act. 28. 4. No doubt this man is a Murderer, whom, though he hath eſcaped the Sea, yet vengeance (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Goddeſs of Juſtice,</hi> ſaith <hi>Vatablus) ſuffereth not to live.</hi> They acknowledged that there was a <hi>Nemeſis,</hi> a <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive power</hi> ſomewhere, that would not fail to execute <hi>vengeance</hi> upon men of bloud: the bloud wil cry ſtill, when the man is dead and buried, that owned it. And thus it is here, <hi>Vox de Terra,</hi> a voice out of the earth, but yet a voice that (like the crie of <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſin) reacheth up to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and a voice that purſues the Murderer down to <hi>Hell. John Baptiſt</hi> was the <hi>voice of one crying in the Wilderneſs, Iſa.</hi> 40. 3. but this is the <hi>voice of one crying in the earth,</hi> and crying out of the earth. That voice out of the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs called for <hi>Repentance;</hi> but this voice out of the Earth calls for <hi>Juſtice.</hi> We read of the <hi>Wizards</hi> in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 19. that they did <hi>peep and mutter out of the earth. Forerius</hi> ſaith, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there rendred <hi>Familiar Spirits,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Forer. in Iſa. 8. 19.</note> were <hi>ſpiritus in ſepulchris mortuorum, &amp; locis ſubterraneis,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97614:9"/>
qui Rogati voce ſtridula reſpondebant;</hi> ſome ſubterranean ſpirits lying in the ſepulchres of the dead, which gave an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to thoſe that conſulted them, in a ſtrange kind of hiſſing voice. But now, as if <hi>Necromancie</hi> and <hi>Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft</hi> were but a petty ſin to this; the bloud of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent doth not <hi>peep and mutter,</hi> but <hi>cry and roar</hi> out of the earth. And when the Murtherers think 'tis ſafe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and there ſhall be no more tidings of it, when they have hid it, and buried it, and hope it is forgotten, even then there is <hi>ſpiritus in ſepulchris mortuorum,</hi> a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the ſepulchres of the dead, that lifts up its voice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, and cries out in the words of <hi>Job, O earth, cover not thou my bloud, Job.</hi> 16. 18. And thus we have found it true by experience; there was <hi>ſpiritus in ſepulchr<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Regis,</hi> a ſpirit of vengeance that cried out of the <hi>Kings Grave,</hi> and never left crying till the <hi>curſe</hi> came a <hi>dozen years</hi> after upon the <hi>ſhedders</hi> of it. Which brings me from the <hi>Cry</hi> to the <hi>Curſe,</hi> the ſecond part of my Text, <hi>And now art thou curſed from the earth, which hath open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her mouth to receive thy brothers bloud from thy hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cain</hi> was curſed <hi>preſently,</hi> though the curſe did not <hi>preſently</hi> overtake him in all the <hi>parts</hi> of it: ſo are all <hi>Murderers,</hi> ſo eſpecially were theſe. No ſooner is the <hi>ſtroke</hi> given, but the <hi>curſe</hi> falls; as the <hi>Bullet</hi> is at the <hi>Mark</hi> in the very inſtant that the <hi>Powder</hi> fires, ſo ſaith God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Nunc maledictus es, Now,</hi> at this very <hi>inſtant, thou art curſed, &amp;c.</hi> But before I come to take notice of the <hi>Curſe</hi> it ſelf, and to compare the curſe of <hi>Cain</hi> with the curſe of <hi>King-killers,</hi> I ſhall crave leave a little further to compare the <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſitions</hi> of theſe men, with the <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſition of Cain;</hi> that when we have ſeen how well they agree in their <hi>Qualities,</hi> we
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97614:10"/>
may the more admire the <hi>juſtice</hi> of God, who hath made them to agree ſo well together in their <hi>Curſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. It is obſerved by the Jews that <hi>Cain</hi> was grown upon the matter an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> before he ſlew his brother. There is in the <hi>Jeruſalem Targum,</hi> a <hi>Dialogue</hi> of what paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> in the field. <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abel, There is no judgment, nor Judge, nor any other World after this; there ſhall no Reward be given to the Juſt, nor revenge taken of the Wicked; the World was not created by the Mercy of God, nor is it governed by his Mercy: why elſe was thy offering accepted and not mine?</hi> And <hi>Abel</hi> anſwered, <hi>There is a judgment, and there is a Judge, and a World to come, and a Reward for the Juſt, and vengeance for the wicked; The World was created by the Mercy of God, and is governed by his Mercy; becauſe my works were better then thine, therefore my offering was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted and thine not.</hi> Thus they contended together in the <hi>field,</hi> and then <hi>Cain</hi> roſe up againſt his brother and ſlew him. <hi>Jonathan Ben Uz<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el</hi> adds, <hi>Fixit lapidem in fronte ejus, &amp; interfecit eum,</hi> He beat out his brains with a ſtone. So that (I ſay) taking it upon the Authority of theſe <hi>ancient Paraphraſts,</hi> it appears to be at leaſt their <hi>Opinion,</hi> that the <hi>Devil</hi> had firſt tempted <hi>Cain</hi> to Atheiſm, to a disbelief of <hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>the World to come,</hi> before he could tempt him to <hi>Murder.</hi> And truly, I think our <hi>King killers</hi> were of <hi>Cains</hi> Religion, that is, of <hi>none,</hi> as arrand <hi>Atheiſts</hi> as he. It ſeems to me impoſſible, that ſuch a ſin ſhould have been committed, by men that did believe a <hi>judgment to come,</hi> or had any thing of <hi>Faith,</hi> or of the <hi>fear of God</hi> left in them: So that as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith of <hi>Cain, Nec dum fratricida, fideicida fuit,</hi> he had<note place="margin">Bern<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ser. 25. ſuper Cant.</note> cut the <hi>Throat</hi> of his own <hi>Faith,</hi> before he killed his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. We may ſay the ſame of theſe men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97614:10"/>
               <hi>fideicidae,</hi> before they were <hi>Regicidae,</hi> Men of <hi>no Religion,</hi> before they could act a Villany, that was ſo contrary to <hi>all Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>Cain</hi> talked with <hi>Abel</hi> his brother, before he ſlew him, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. Some underſtand it thus; That <hi>Cain</hi> for the preſent, <hi>diſſembled his Anger,</hi> and gave his brother <hi>good words,</hi> that he might get him out into the <hi>field,</hi> and have the fitter <hi>oportunity</hi> to kill him. And then, here is in <hi>Cain</hi> a notable example of a <hi>bloudy hypocrite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> who <hi>fawns and flatters,</hi> that he may <hi>kill and deſtroy.</hi> So <hi>Joab</hi> took <hi>Abner aſide in the gate to ſpeak with him quietly, and ſmote him there under the fifth rib, that he died, 2 Sam.</hi> 3. 27. And as if our <hi>King-killers</hi> had learned this <hi>craft</hi> from their <hi>Father Cain</hi> himſelf, they held the <hi>King</hi> with pretended <hi>Parlees,</hi> and <hi>Treaties,</hi> and a ſeeming <hi>deſire of accord,</hi> even when the hearts of many of them were fully ſet to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him. God deliver us, and the Kingdom from ſuch <hi>Crocodiles,</hi> who weep over the <hi>head,</hi> when they have a mind to feed upon the <hi>brain;</hi> from ſuch <hi>Judas's,</hi> who have <hi>oyl</hi> upon their <hi>tongues,</hi> whileſt they have <hi>murder</hi> in their <hi>hearts, whoſe words are ſmoother then butter, and yet they are drawn ſwords, Pſal.</hi> 55. 21.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Joſephus</hi> tells us, That <hi>Cain</hi> after he had killed his<note place="margin">Joſeph. Antiq. lib. 1. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>brother,</hi> and was gone out from the preſence of the Lord, turned <hi>Robber,</hi> and ſo became the <hi>firſt Robber</hi> as well as the <hi>firſt Murtherer</hi> in the world. And here certainly our <hi>King-killers</hi> have out-gone him. As the whole world cannot match them in <hi>bloud-guiltineſs,</hi> ſo neither can it equal them in <hi>Robbery.</hi> The <hi>Tartars</hi> themſelves, among whom <hi>Theevery</hi> is tolerated by a Law, were never ſo great <hi>Theeves</hi> as theſe. They Robbed <hi>three Kingdoms</hi> of their <hi>lawful Soveraign,</hi> and they robbed the <hi>lawful heir</hi> of his <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and they robbed the <hi>Church</hi> of its <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97614:11"/>
and in doing ſo, <hi>they robbed God, Mal.</hi> 3. 8. They robbed the <hi>People</hi> of their <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and they robbed the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of their <hi>maintenance;</hi> they robbed the <hi>Nation</hi> of infinite <hi>ſumms of Money,</hi> and they robbed <hi>hundreds of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> of their whole <hi>Eſtates.</hi> And (which was worſe) they did what they could, to rob us all of that which is deareſt to us, <hi>our Religion and Chriſtianity.</hi> Never were there ſuch <hi>Robbers</hi> in the world as theſe; here <hi>Cain</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf lies behind, and cannot come near them.</p>
            <p>4. And as they were more <hi>Notorious Robbers,</hi> ſo they were more <hi>impudent Murderers</hi> then ever <hi>Cain</hi> was. He drew his brother out into the <hi>field,</hi> a private place; his <hi>Conſcience</hi> being (it ſeems) ſo ſtartled at the <hi>Guilt</hi> of his ſin, that though the World was ſo thinly peopled, that there were none but his <hi>near Relations</hi> on earth, yet he durſt not commit it <hi>openly,</hi> but drew him into a <hi>ſecret place,</hi> thinking to <hi>conceal</hi> the Murder, and probably to have made ſuch an excuſe to his <hi>Father,</hi> as <hi>Joſephs bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> did to their <hi>Father Jacob, That ſome evil beaſt had torn him in pieces, Gen.</hi> 37. 33. ſo hainous a ſin is <hi>Murder</hi> in the eyes even of <hi>wicked men,</hi> that it is aſhamed to walk <hi>bare-faced,</hi> though the ſword of <hi>Humane Vengeance</hi> be not drawn to purſue it. But theſe wretches acted their vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany in the <hi>moſt publique place of the Kingdom:</hi> as if <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> were now become <hi>Meritorious,</hi> and the <hi>greateſt of Crimes</hi> durſt impudently proclaim it ſelf to be a <hi>Vertue. They poured out this ſacred bloud upon the top of a Rock, and poured it not upon the Ground to cover it with duſt, that it might cauſe fury to come up to take vengeance Ezek.</hi> 24. 7, 8. ſo that <hi>Cain</hi> was a <hi>modeſt, ſhame-fac'd Murderer,</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with theſe men. S. <hi>Hierom</hi> tells us from the Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Hieron. in Ezek. 27.</note> of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that the place in which <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew his brother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was the <hi>Field of Damaſous,</hi> which thence took its
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97614:11"/>
name <hi>Sanguinem Bibens,</hi> Drinking Bloud. And there was as much reaſon that the place where this ſacred bloud was ſhed, ſhould have been called <hi>Aceldama,</hi> The field of Bloud, had there not been ſome kinde of <hi>Expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> made, by ſhedding the bloud of ſome of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers <hi>near the ſame place.</hi> And ſo the <hi>curſe</hi> fell upon them in a moſt <hi>exemplary</hi> way; as if God had ſaid to every one of them in particular, as he did here to <hi>Cain, And now thou art curſed from the Earth</hi> (from that very ſame Earth) <hi>which hath opened her mouth to receive, &amp;c.</hi> which brings me about again to a more particular ſurvey of the <hi>Curſe it ſelf,</hi> and the <hi>correſpondence</hi> that may be obſerved, as well in the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> as in the <hi>Sin,</hi> of <hi>Cain</hi> and theſe <hi>Murderers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maledictus tu à Terrâ,</hi> that's a heavy Curſe. You may obſerve the difference between <hi>Adams</hi> curſe and <hi>Cains; Adams</hi> was <hi>Maledicta Terra propter te,</hi> Gen. 3. 17. the curſe lighted mainly upon the earth: but <hi>Cains</hi> curſe came home, and lighted upon his own perſon, <hi>Maledictus tu à terra,</hi> curſed art thou from the earth. That was, <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the earth for thy ſake;</hi> but this is, <hi>Curſed be thou for the earths ſake.</hi> When God curſeth a mans <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Poſſeſsions,</hi> it is not half ſo much, as when he curſeth <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> his <hi>ſoul and body.</hi> But <hi>Cains</hi> was both, a <hi>double curſe;</hi> he was curſed and the earth too. <hi>Curſed art thou,</hi> there's the curſe upon his <hi>Perſon;</hi> and <hi>the earth ſhall not yield her increaſe,</hi> there's the curſe upon his <hi>Poſſeſsions.</hi> One <hi>ſingle curſe</hi> is not enough for ſuch <hi>Murderers,</hi> they are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with <hi>curſe upon curſe, Curſed in their Basket, and in their Store; Curſed in the City, and in the Field:</hi> So was <hi>Cain;</hi> he built a <hi>City,</hi> but (it ſeems) ſtayed not long in it; the <hi>furies of his Conſcience</hi> (as 'tis thought) drove him out into the <hi>Field</hi> again, and the <hi>City</hi> was called by his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97614:12"/>
               <hi>Sons name, ver.</hi> 17. And laſtly, <hi>Curſed in the fruit of their Body, and in the fruit of their Ground, and in the fruit of their Cattel. Deut.</hi> 28. 16, &amp;c. All this came home upon <hi>Cain.</hi> And the heavieſt of all <hi>temporal curſes</hi> is, when God (who often <hi>viſiteth the ſins of the Fathers upon the Children</hi>) doth curſe the <hi>fruit of a wicked mans body,</hi> and gives him <hi>curſed children</hi> for his <hi>curſed ſins. Cain</hi> was curſed in his <hi>ſoul,</hi> and curſed in his <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his <hi>poſterity.</hi> His <hi>children</hi> were <hi>curſed</hi> children, not one of them came to good. Their <hi>wickedneſs</hi> infected the whole world, and brought the <hi>Floud,</hi> and that <hi>Floud</hi> ſwept all the <hi>poſterity of Cain</hi> away, not one left. I do not wiſh this <hi>curſe</hi> upon the <hi>children of our King-killers;</hi> rather let them live to ſee all their <hi>Fathers ſins which they have done, and conſider and do not ſuch like, that they may not die in the iniquity of their Fathers, Ezek.</hi> 18 14, 17.</p>
            <p>And now, let us conſider how God hath brought home the reſt of <hi>Cains curſe</hi> upon the children of <hi>Cain,</hi> thoſe <hi>men of bloud</hi> that murdered the King; and by the <hi>dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> of the curſe, learn for ever to <hi>deteſt and abhor</hi> the ſin. The cry of that <hi>Royal bloud</hi> you have heard already, and all the Land heard it, and groaned under it for many years; but now the <hi>Curſe</hi> hath overtaken the <hi>Cry.</hi> We will purſue it <hi>ſtep by ſtep,</hi> that we may ſee and admire the <hi>juſtice of God</hi> in the <hi>exemplary</hi> puniſhment of that <hi>enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> ſin.</p>
            <p>1. That the earth was curſed that received the <hi>bloud of Abel, ver. 12. When thou tilleſt the ground it ſhall not henceforth yield her increaſe.</hi> We are told that <hi>bloud de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth a Land, Num.</hi> 35. 33. that it doth ever; and the <hi>Land cannot be cleanſed of the bloud that is ſhed therein, but by the bloud of him that ſhed it.</hi> Therefore there was no <hi>ſatisfaction to be taken for the life of a Murderer,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97614:12"/>
the Land could not otherwiſe be purged, <hi>ver.</hi> 31. ſo ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov. 28. 17. A man that doth violence to the bloud of any perſon, ſhall flee to the pit, let no man ſtay him:</hi> that is, let him die <hi>without Mercy,</hi> let no man <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate</hi> for him. But beſide this, <hi>A bloudy Land</hi> being thus defiled, is ſometimes in Gods judgment, made a <hi>barren Land:</hi> and the <hi>ſoaking</hi> of an Eſtate in <hi>bloud,</hi> is equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to the ſowing of it with <hi>ſalt. Pſal. 107. 34. A fruitful land turneth he into barrenneſs, for the wickedneſs of them that dwell therein.</hi> The Country of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> was turned into a <hi>ſalt Lake,</hi> for the wickedneſs of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. Thus doth Gods <hi>curſe</hi> many times get into <hi>wicked mens eſtates,</hi> ſo that they crumble away without any other reaſon to be given, further then that the <hi>Flying Rowl is conſuming the beams and the timber, Zach.</hi> 5. 4. Let them look to that, who have built their <hi>houſes in bloud.</hi> This is certain, That the curſe for this Murder did hover a long time, like an <hi>Eagle</hi> over the whole Kingdom, which hath been by reaſon of it, for many years a <hi>Land of Nod,</hi> that is, a <hi>Land of trembling.</hi> There was a <hi>cup of trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling</hi> put into our hands, and we were made to drink the <hi>wine of aſtoniſhment,</hi> and were never quiet till this bloud was revenged. <hi>The voice</hi> of it <hi>ſhook</hi> the whole kingdom, and <hi>ſhattered</hi> it in pieces. And ſo part of the Curſe fell upon the Earth.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Cain</hi> himſelf was curſed that ſhed this bloud. And this is one great part of his curſe, that he ſhould be a <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive and Vagabond upon the earth, ver.</hi> 12. that is, That he ſhould be purſued hither and thither, by the <hi>Furies</hi> of his own <hi>Conſcience,</hi> driven up and down the world, as one that is purſued with a <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> by the <hi>Miniſters of Juſtice,</hi> ſo that he ſhould never find a quiet <hi>Habitation</hi> more as long as he lived. So <hi>Junius</hi> expounds this part
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97614:13"/>
of the Curſe, that by it is meant, <hi>Corporis &amp; animi inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas, ex diris conſcientiae,</hi> the unſettledneſs both of his body and mind, through the terrours of his Conſcience. And thus <hi>Euripides</hi> brings in <hi>Oreſtes</hi> after he had ſlain his mother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, running up and down <hi>Greece,</hi> having his Conſcience ſtung, like a <hi>Beaſt</hi> that is pricked with a <hi>Fly,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſo never able to be quiet any where. This <hi>puniſhment</hi> was very exemplary in the <hi>Jews,</hi> after they had crucified the <hi>Lord of Life; Diſperſi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. Apol. c. 21.</note> 
               <hi>palabundi, coeli &amp; ſoli ſui ext<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rres, vagantur per orbem; ſine homine, ſine Deo Rege,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi> They had never a certain abiding place ſince, but as <hi>baniſhed</hi> men, they put in where they may be permitted to live; never a <hi>Temple,</hi> nor <hi>publique Sacrifice;</hi> never a <hi>King</hi> to govern them, nor a <hi>God</hi> to take care of them. Inſomuch that <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephorus</hi> calls them <hi>Theatrum Vindicta Divinae,</hi> the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre of Divine Vengeance. And this was <hi>Cains</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; He was not yet in Hell, but Hell was got into him, and that made him <hi>reſtleſs,</hi> endeavouring (if it had been poſſible) to <hi>flee from himſelf,</hi> as carrying his own <hi>Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> in his own <hi>boſome.</hi> The <hi>Guilt</hi> of his ſoul ſet Spurs (as it were) to his <hi>body<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and made him continually to be in a reſtleſs motion. And this (if you conſider it) is the very Curſe that is fallen upon the <hi>Regicides,</hi> thoſe of them eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that have hitherto eſcaped the <hi>Sword of Juſtice.</hi> They are in the <hi>Land of Nod, Mobilis &amp; Vag<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> frighted with the Noiſe of the <hi>Fetters</hi> of their own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and ſtill afraid leſt they hear the feet of the <hi>Revenger of bloud</hi> behind them. Thus is that Curſe fallen upon them, then which <hi>David</hi> (by the Spirit of <hi>Propheſie</hi>) could not <hi>imprecate</hi> a greater upon the enemies of God and his Church, <hi>Pſal. 109. 10. Let them be continually Vagabonds, and ſeek their bread out of deſolate places.</hi> Indeed we read
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97614:13"/>
in Scripture of a company of <hi>holy Vagabonds,</hi> that did <hi>wander about in Sheeps-skins, and Goats-skins, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, afflicted, and tormented, of whom the world was not worthy, they wandred in Deſarts, and in Mountains, and in Dens, and Caves of the earth, Heb.</hi> 11. 37, 38. This was not their <hi>curſe,</hi> becauſe not for any <hi>crime;</hi> nor their <hi>miſery,</hi> but their <hi>happineſs.</hi> The <hi>world</hi> was not worthy of them, though they were not thought <hi>worthy</hi> to live in the <hi>world.</hi> But to wander as <hi>Cain</hi> did, with a <hi>guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> up and down the world, this is a <hi>Curſe</hi> indeed, the very curſe that the remaining <hi>Regicides</hi> are now under.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Cain deſpaired</hi> when he heard his ſentence. <hi>My pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is greater then I can bear;</hi> or as others read it, <hi>My ſin is greater then can be forgiven.</hi> He that before could not be brought to <hi>Repentance</hi> with the ſight of his <hi>ſin,</hi> is now upon the ſight of his <hi>puniſhment,</hi> dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>deſparation.</hi> And this S. <hi>Bernard</hi> calls the greateſt<note place="margin">Bern Ser. 3. de S. Andr.</note> of <hi>Cains</hi> ſins; <hi>Grande illud ſcelus evomuit, major eſt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas m<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a,</hi> &amp;c. He <hi>vomited</hi> out (ſaith he) that great <hi>blaſphemy, My ſin is greater then can be forgiven.</hi> A ſin that is injurious, 1. To the <hi>Mercy of God;</hi> for it makes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God to be weaker then Sin, weaker then the Devil, as if his <hi>Mercy</hi> muſt be triumphed over, and <hi>led captive</hi> by Satans <hi>malice.</hi> And therefore S. <hi>Bernard</hi> having repeated thoſe prodigious words of <hi>Cain, My ſin is greater then can be forgiven,</hi> cries out, <hi>Mentiris Latro,</hi> Thou lyeſt Villain, <hi>Major enim eſt Dei pietas quam quaevis iniquitas,</hi> for the Mercy of God is greater then any iniquity of man. 2. To <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the <hi>Merits of Chriſt;</hi> For it is to charge the Death and Paſſion of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> with weakneſs, and impotency, and inſufficiency; as if the <hi>Devil</hi> were more mighty to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy,</hi> then <hi>Chriſt</hi> is to <hi>ſave.</hi> To which the ſame <hi>Father</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. ſuper C<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. Ser. 61.</note> replies again, <hi>Quid tam ad mortem quod non Chriſti morte
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97614:14"/>
ſalvetur?</hi> What ſin is there ſo deadly, that <hi>Chriſts bloud</hi> cannot heal? Yea, but <hi>Cain</hi> (ſaith he) was not a <hi>member</hi> of Chriſt, and therefore had nothing to do with the <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> of Chriſt. He could not ſay, <hi>Quod mihi deeſt, uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po mihi ex veſceribus domini,</hi> I will fetch <hi>honey</hi> out of the <hi>howels</hi> of the <hi>Lyon</hi> of the <hi>Tribe of Judah; quoe viſcera per vulnera patent,</hi> whoſe very <hi>bowels</hi> you may ſee through his <hi>bleeding wounds.</hi> 3. It is utterly deſtructive to true <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Repentance,</hi> and ſo a ſin againſt the very <hi>Remedy.</hi> For this is it which makes wretched ſinners <hi>deſperate,</hi> when they look upon God as all <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Fury, Wrath</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, Vengeance</hi> and <hi>Terrour,</hi> but they apprehend nothing of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Compaſsion</hi> in him. This was it that made <hi>Judas</hi> hang himſelf, and <hi>Cain</hi> run from God. And truly, I am afraid this Curſe fell upon many of the <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides</hi> too; upon ſome the <hi>curſe of Deſperation,</hi> upon moſt of them the <hi>curſe of Obduration,</hi> that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a hard and impenitent heart, Rom.</hi> 2. 5. S. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith<note place="margin">Greg. Mag. in Pſal. 51. 11.</note> upon this ſpeech of <hi>Cain,</hi> that he committed the ſin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> I dare not ſay this was that ſin, but if<note place="margin">Aug. Expoſ. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ep. ad Rom.</note> we may judge by S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who makes it to lie mainly in <hi>final impenitency joyned with deſperation,</hi> I doubt many of the <hi>Regicides</hi> came as near to it as <hi>Charing-Croſs</hi> is to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> None of them (that ever I heard) even when they came to <hi>Execution,</hi> manifeſted any great ſigns of <hi>Repentance,</hi> for this horrid <hi>Murder;</hi> ſome died <hi>ſtupidly,</hi> others <hi>juſtified</hi> it, others <hi>excuſed</hi> it. They that are yet alive, have their <hi>hearts</hi> hard enough, were their <hi>hands</hi> but ſtrong enough to act over the ſame ſin again. So that here too is <hi>Cains</hi> Curſe right, <hi>The plague of an impenitent heart is fallen upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. <hi>Cain</hi> was afraid that <hi>every one that met him, would ſlay him:</hi> ſuch was the terrour of his <hi>guilty conſcience,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97614:14"/>
that he took himſelf to be an <hi>Anathema,</hi> an <hi>execrable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted perſon,</hi> an <hi>Outlaw</hi> that any one might kill that would. Nay, not only ſo, but the word may be read in<note place="margin">Fagius in loc.</note> the <hi>Neuter Gender, Quicquid invenerit me,</hi> &amp;c. whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever doth meet me, will ſlay me. And ſo he was afraid not only of <hi>men,</hi> but of the <hi>beaſts,</hi> and <hi>creeping things,</hi> and <hi>fowls of the air.</hi> He was afraid leſt God ſhould arm the very <hi>irrational creatures</hi> to be the <hi>Revengers</hi> of this bloud. As (you know) God ſent <hi>Hornets</hi> to drive out the <hi>Canaanites, Exod.</hi> 23. 28. and commanded <hi>Bears</hi> to tear in pieces thoſe <hi>lewd children</hi> that mocked the <hi>Prophet, 2 King.</hi> 2. 24. And this very <hi>terrour of Cain,</hi> leſt <hi>every thing that met him ſhould ſlay him,</hi> lay upon the <hi>hearts</hi> of our <hi>King-killers</hi> too. A <hi>Panick fear</hi> ſurpriſed them, as it is the property of the <hi>Workers of Iniquity, to be afraid where no fear is, Pſ.</hi> 53. 5. They were <hi>ſcared</hi> with their own <hi>ſhadows,</hi> and (if Report lye not) with their own <hi>dreams;</hi> the very thoughts of their hearts were as ſo many <hi>Scorpions</hi> ſtill ſtinging them, and that in the time of their greateſt Proſperity. They lived in perpetual <hi>Frights</hi> and <hi>Fears</hi> as wretched <hi>Cain</hi> did. And ſo this part of the Curſe fell upon them too; <hi>They were afraid that every one that met them would ſlay them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. <hi>The Lord ſet a Mark upon Cain,</hi> which was partly to <hi>ſecure him</hi> from his fears of being killed by the next he met, and partly <hi>to warn others</hi> by his example to take heed of ſhedding bloud. What this <hi>Mark</hi> was, is very uncertain. Some of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers have a <hi>fanſie</hi> that it was a <hi>Dog</hi> which always kept him company, and ſuffered no perſon to come near him. <hi>A fanſie</hi> that will ſuit well enough with <hi>our King-killers,</hi> who (no doubt) had a <hi>Dog</hi> to wait upon them ever after; they were <hi>dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> with the <hi>terrours</hi> of their <hi>guilty conſcience,</hi> which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97614:15"/>
followed them ſtill cloſe at the <hi>heels,</hi> till vengeance over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took them. Others ſay, it was a <hi>truculent bloudy aſpect,</hi> that frighted all that came near him, ſo that they would ſay, <hi>Fugiamus hinc, iſte eſt crudelis ille homicida, qui fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fag. in ver. 16.</note> 
               <hi>ſuum occidit;</hi> let us flee hence, this is that cruel <hi>Murderer,</hi> who killed his <hi>Brother.</hi> Others again ſay, It was a <hi>perpetual trembling of all his members;</hi> which they gather from the <hi>Septuagints</hi> Tranſlation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that he ſhould go up and down the world <hi>groaning</hi> and <hi>trembling.</hi> Laſtly, others will have it to be a <hi>continual trembling of the earth</hi> under him, ſo that it made all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons afraid to come near him; and this they gather from the <hi>Land of Nod,</hi> that is, the <hi>Land of Trembling,</hi> in which he dwelt, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. Whether the <hi>earth did ſhake</hi> under <hi>Cain,</hi> I know not; ſure enough the whole <hi>Kingdom ſhook</hi> under the Murderers of the King. Be the <hi>Mark</hi> what it will, it was that which made him an <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Terrour</hi> to others, and a greater terrour then his <hi>death</hi> could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have been. Our Law condemns <hi>Notorious Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers</hi> to be hanged on a <hi>Gibbet,</hi> there to rot, and this <hi>in terrorem.</hi> Now ſuppoſe <hi>Cain</hi> had been ſerved ſo, in leſs then twenty years there had been no <hi>Mark</hi> nor <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Perſon,</hi> nor perhaps of ſuch a <hi>Sin.</hi> But now that <hi>Cain</hi> was driven up and down the world, for the ſpace (as 'tis conceived) of ſeveral hundred years with Gods <hi>Mark</hi> upon him, as a <hi>living, walking Monument</hi> of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, this was ſuch a <hi>puniſhment,</hi> as was moſt likely to effect the ends for which God appointed it, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>deterr others</hi> from Murder. And ſurely God hath ſet a <hi>Mark</hi> upon theſe Murderers too, enough (I hope) to deterr <hi>all but themſelves</hi> from the like ſin. He hath ſet a <hi>Mark of infamy</hi> upon them and theirs; he hath made them an <hi>aſtoniſhment</hi> to themſelves and the World; and (which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97614:15"/>
is worſe) he hath (as I noted before) ſet a <hi>mark upon the ſouls</hi> and <hi>conſciences</hi> of many of them; he hath <hi>ſeared them with an hot iron, 1 Tim.</hi> 4. 2. and given them up (as it is to be feared) <hi>to a reprobate mind, Rom.</hi> 1. 28. ſo they have <hi>Cains Mark</hi> upon them; and in this alſo they ſhare in his puniſhment, as well as in his ſin.</p>
            <p>6. <hi>Cain</hi> (being condemned) with his Mark upon him, <hi>went out from the preſence of the Lord ver.</hi> 16. That is, <hi>Ab Eccleſia fidelium ex<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lavit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fagius,</hi> He was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from the Church and Ordinances of God; he never frequented them more, nor <hi>offered ſacrifice</hi> more, after he had killed his brother. And being thus caſt out of the Church, he loſt the <hi>light of Gods countenance,</hi> which was ſo ſad a part of his Curſe, that <hi>Cain</hi> himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of it, <hi>ver. 14. And from thy face</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall I be hid. Gregory the great</hi> upon that paſſage of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 51. 11. Caſt me not away from thy preſence, &amp;c.</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>A facie Dei projicitur, cut ſpies veniae poſt peccatum negatur;</hi> He is caſt out from the preſence of the Lord, who grows <hi>deſperate</hi> after ſin committed. <hi>Cain</hi> was now in a deſperate condition, and cries out, <hi>From thy face ſhall I be hid;</hi> that is, I ſhall never approach near thy <hi>Gracious preſence</hi> more, I ſhall be out of thy <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and <hi>ſpecial favour.</hi> So <hi>Gods hiding of his face,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth the withdrawing of his <hi>comforts, care,</hi> and <hi>prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> from a perſon, <hi>Pſal. 13. 1. How long wilt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get me, O Lord, for ever? how long wilt thou hide thy face from me?</hi> Gods <hi>hiding his face</hi> from a man, is his <hi>forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of him; and his <hi>forgetting</hi> of him is nothing elſe, out his leaving him out of his <hi>protection</hi> and <hi>ſpecial favour.</hi> It is the withdrawing of the <hi>light of his countenance</hi> from a man, which if it be for a ſeaſon, is called <hi>Deſertion;</hi> if for ever, it is <hi>Hell:</hi> ſo that when <hi>Cain</hi> was gone out from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97614:16"/>
the <hi>preſence of the Lord,</hi> he was (as it were) in <hi>Hell,</hi> while he was upon <hi>Earth.</hi> And this part of the Curſe is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently fulfilled upon the <hi>Regicides</hi> and their <hi>Adherents,</hi> who have voluntarily pulled down <hi>Cains curſe</hi> upon their own ſouls; and by excluding, and ſeparating themſelves from the <hi>Church and Communion</hi> of Gods people, have <hi>gone out from the Preſence of the Lord.</hi> This is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, that the greateſt part of them never <hi>cared to come near God</hi> in his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> in any part of his <hi>Publick Worſhip,</hi> ſince they <hi>killed the King.</hi> God indeed <hi>hid his face from Cain,</hi> but theſe men have <hi>hid their faces from God,</hi> and run out from his preſence without driving: which is ſo exemplary a Curſe upon them, that <hi>he that runs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> may read it.</hi> For as <hi>Cain,</hi> after he went out from the <hi>preſence of the Lord,</hi> was <hi>Mobilis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Vagus,</hi> a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Runnagate, that could never be quiet in a place: ſo theſe men, after they had forſaken the <hi>Communion of our Church,</hi> were never ſetled in any thing, but ran from <hi>Errour</hi> to <hi>Errour,</hi> and from <hi>Deluſion</hi> to <hi>Deluſion</hi> till many of them had quite caſt off the <hi>profeſsion of Chriſtianity.</hi> Theſe were <hi>they who ſeparated themſelves, ſenſual, having not the ſpirit,</hi> which they ſo much gloried in, <hi>Jude 19. They went out from the preſence of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>7. And laſtly, It is a received Opinion among the Jews, that <hi>Cain,</hi> running about in the Woods, was killed by <hi>Lamech</hi> inſtead of a wild Beaſt, in the ſeventh Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſo he met with his reward at laſt, though it<note place="margin">Aug. Qu. ex Vet. Teſt qu 6.</note> were long firſt. I know S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> denies this, upon the account that <hi>Lamech</hi> was not the <hi>ſeventh,</hi> but the <hi>fifth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. ad Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſum. Ep. 125</note> from <hi>Cain;</hi> but S. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſo far defends it, as that it was <hi>majorum noſtrorum ſententia,</hi> an old Tradition that <hi>Cain</hi> was killed by <hi>Lamech,</hi> who was the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> though not from <hi>Cain.</hi> And this is that which we may
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97614:16"/>
reſt ſomewhat ſecure of too, that as God hath given ſome of theſe wretches their reward in a great deal leſs time; ſo for thoſe that yet remain, the <hi>Revenger of bloud</hi> will purſue them, and at laſt, overtake them too, though they may be ſuffered a while for <hi>greater terrour,</hi> as <hi>Cain</hi> was, to be <hi>Runnagates and Vagabonds upon the Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Tom. 9. Hieron. Ep. 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude all with a ſaying of S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was the Author of that Epiſtle, <hi>Ad Virginem in exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium miſſam,</hi> which is among his Works, <hi>Nullus tam crudelis homicida eſt, quam qui ita erga alterum ſaevit, ut non parcat ſibi,</hi> none ſo <hi>deſperate</hi> a Murderer, as he that will deſtroy himſelf to be revenged upon another. <hi>Cain</hi> never thought what a miſchief he ſhould do to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in killing his brother. For beſide all the former <hi>curſes,</hi> this <hi>miſery</hi> he brought upon himſelf, that now he was deprived of his brothers <hi>company, counſel, and aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> upon all occaſions. And certainly, had not our <hi>King-killers</hi> been poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of ſtrong <hi>deluſion,</hi> they muſt needs have foreſeen, that beſide all the <hi>miſery</hi> they ſhould infallibly bring upon the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> they did but thruſt a <hi>knife</hi> into their own <hi>Throats,</hi> when they <hi>killed the King.</hi> But thus it is, when <hi>God hides his face,</hi> and gives men over to an <hi>infatuated ſpirit.</hi> They were like the <hi>Mad-man</hi> that beat out his own <hi>Brains</hi> with his own <hi>hands; Et immemores ſalutis ſuae, propria manu ſeipſos interimunt, in Reges ſuos proprias convertendo vires,</hi> ſaith<note place="margin">Concil. Tolet. 4. Can. 74.</note> the fourth Council of <hi>Toledo;</hi> And being unmindful of their own ſafety, they kill <hi>themſelves</hi> with their own <hi>hands,</hi> who lift up their <hi>hands</hi> againſt their <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you have ſeen how <hi>Cains Curſe</hi> in every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular is fallen upon the <hi>Regicides;</hi> that we may ſay of them, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> of his Countrymen the Jews, That <hi>wrath is come upon them to the uttermoſt, 1 Theſſ.</hi> 2. 16. And
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97614:17"/>
God grant that the <hi>Curſe</hi> may reſt there, and never flie farther abroad, and that the <hi>Land</hi> may be cleanſed from that <hi>bloud.</hi> And for the Kingdoms peace and ſettlement, let us put up that Prayer to God, which the <hi>children of Iſrael</hi> were taught to pray when a <hi>man was found ſlain in the field,</hi> Deut. 28. 8. <hi>Be merciful, O Lord, be merciful unto thy people whom thou haſt redeemed, and lay not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bloud unto their charge.</hi> O let the <hi>Guilt</hi> of this bloud be forgiven the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> and let the <hi>bloud of Chriſt Jeſus</hi> cry louder for us, then the <hi>bloud of King Charles</hi> againſt us. Even ſo, O Father, for <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> ſake, thy dear Son, our onely Saviour; to whom with thy ſelf, and thy Eternal Spirit, Three Perſons, One Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious God, be all Glory, Praiſe, and Thankſgiving, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97614:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
